So, alright, today's דף daf is דף כף daf Kaf and 20,
we pick up at the bottom of or the middle of י"ט
עמוד ב', Yud Tes Amud Bais, close to the bottom,
and אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, one, two, three, four lines
down in the wide lines. So, אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע,
Amar Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua, הכל מודים, Hakol modim, so we're
in the middle of the issue about רגל Regel interrupting the אבילות
Aveilus and we had a brief learning derivation from a verse from
נזיר Nazir that the idea of 30 days, although that's only specifically
relating to the issue of the hair. And now we are going
back to the issue of the רגל Regel interrupting the אבילות. Aveilus.
Let's take a look. אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע הכל מודים
כשחל שלישי שלו להיות ערב הרגל שאסור ברחיצה עד הערב. Amar Rav
Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua Hakol modim k'shechal shlishi shelo liyos erev ha-Regel,
she-assur birchitza ad ha-erev. Everybody agrees that when the third day, this
is again assuming like the משנה Mishna which we're going to reject
or give the opposite, the opposing opinion in a few minutes, but
assuming like the משנה Mishna that רגל Regel does not interrupt שבעה
Shiva unless a person has observed a full three days. Says, let's
say that the third day is ערב הרגל. Erev HaRegel. So before
we had the idea when the רגל Regel was going to interrupt
שלושים Shloshim and a day seven or a day eight was ערב
הרגל Erev HaRegel that you were allowed a person was allowed to
get a haircut before the רגל. Regel. So even though the רגל
Regel had not yet interrupted, it was about to interrupt and that
allowed the person to get the haircut to prepare for the רגל.
Regel. What about a similar situation relating to the שבעה Shiva and
the person is only finishing up day three? So again, it's with
the idea that the first three days are core and can never
be cut short. That's the assumption of the משנה. Mishna. Can a
person, when those days when the שבעה Shiva is going to be
interrupted, do certain practices during that ערב הרגל Erev HaRegel when it's
still the third day in order to get ready for the רגל?
Regel? And here the statement is that one cannot.
הכל מודים כשחל שלישי שלו להיות ערב הרגל שאסור ברחיצה עד הערב.
Hakol modim k'shechal shlishi shelo liyos erev ha-Regel, she-assur birchitza ad ha-erev.
A person cannot bathe until the nightfall. And again, the reason here
we're mentioning bathing and before we mentioned haircut is bathing is one
of the practices that is distinctive to שבעה. Shiva. אמר רב נחמיה
בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav Nechemia brei d'Rav Yehoshua, so Rav Nechemia
son of Rav Yehoshua said, אשכחינהו לרב פפי ולרב פפא דיתבי ואמרי.
Ashkenu l'Rav Pappi ul'Rav Pappa d'yasvi v'amri. Sound Rav Pappi and Rav
Pappa that were sitting and saying, הלכה כרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע.
Halacha k'Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua. We rule like Rav Huna the
son of Rav Yehoshua about that the person cannot bathe until nightfall.
איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, others say, אמר רב נחמיה בריה דרב יוסף
אשכחינהו לרב פפי ולרב פפא ולרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav
Nechemia brei d'Rav Yosef Ashkenu l'Rav Pappi ul'Rav Pappa ul'Rav Huna brei
d'Rav Yehoshua, that no, Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua hadn't said it
prior and then it was being affirmed by Rav Pappi and Rav
Pappa, but Rav Pappi and Rav Pappa and Rav Huna brei d'Rav
Yehoshua, all three of them at this time saying,
הכל מודים כשחל שלישי שלו להיות ערב הרגל שאסור ברחיצה עד הערב,
Hakol modim k'shechal shlishi shelo liyos erev ha-Regel, she-assur birchitza ad ha-erev,
that everybody agrees that if day three falls ערב הרגל, Erev HaRegel,
a person cannot bathe until nightfall. Now, how much so here the
גמרא Gemara pretty much ends that discussion right now and that seems
to be the הלכה. Halacha. Nobody debates it. Now, we don't פוסקין
pasken three days, but what if you had an analogous case that
a person day one,
you know, buried a relative ערב הרגל, Erev HaRegel, literally ערב הרגל,
Erev HaRegel, day one was ערב הרגל, Erev HaRegel, they had some
practices of אבילות, Aveilus, you know, on that day and now the
רגל Regel was going to cut you know, cut off שבעה? Shiva?
Would the person have to wait until nightfall in order to bathe?
Would you say this thing? Logically, you should. However, would they have
to wait until nightfall to do any of the practices of שבעה,
Shiva, you know, that the רגל Regel will interrupt? So there's a
question exactly how to read this. Some want to read that this
is specifically about bathing because a person can bathe during the רגל.
Regel. Now, question about bathing in hot water, you know, you can
do a person according to the גמרא Gemara you could do your
face and hands and feet in hot water, but not your whole
body.
Questions nowadays about that when people normally do bathe their whole bodies
in water. Many פוסקים Poskim allow a person to take a hot
shower on יום טוב, Yom Tov, although not a bath because that
had to do with certain גזירות gezeiros and so on. But anyway,
but some understand that the reason we're able to be strict here,
I mean, why should on the one hand, you could say, well,
it's שבעה. Shiva. We're never going to compromise שבעה, Shiva, or at
least the core three days or the core one day even for
the sake of רגל. Regel. But another sort of counterargument is, but
that might only be because bathing is something that you're reasonably would
be able to do on the רגל Regel itself as opposed to
things that you might not be reasonably able to do on the
רגל. Regel. Others want to also read it that when it says
that you're forbidden עד הערב, ad ha-erev, עד הערב ad ha-erev does
not mean until it's actually יום טוב, Yom Tov, but it means
until it's late afternoon and very close to יום טוב. Yom Tov.
That you can't do it early in the morning, you have to
wait till it's much closer to יום טוב. Yom Tov. So although
this גמרא Gemara seems to be limiting in terms of this scenario,
להלכה l'Halacha we
really we don't פוסקין pasken it so much. We either understand עד
הערב ad ha-erev to be that when it gets closer to the
afternoon you're allowed to do, late afternoon you're allowed to do it,
and to limit it at most to the issue of bathing, which
is something that a person could reasonably do once it already becomes
יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara continues.
בעי מיניה אביי מרבה, Ba'ei minei Abaye me'Rabba, well has here the
גרסא. girsa. So Abaye asked רבה Rabba the following question.
קברו ברגל רגל עולה למנין שלשים או אין רגל עולה למנין שלשים?
Kivaro be'regel, regel oleh le'minyan shloshim o ein regel oleh le'minyan shloshim?
If a person was, you know, buried a relative during the יום
טוב, Yom Tov, would the רגל regel count for שלשים shloshim or
not? Now we had already said, I'll just sort of tell you
what the משנה Mishna says on the הלכה, halacha, we had already
said in the משנה Mishna that רגל regel is מפסיק ואינו עולה.
mafsik ve'eino oleh. It interrupts but it doesn't count towards. Now what,
why would you need it to count towards the period if it
already interrupts? So the scenario is somebody is buried during the רגל,
regel, and the time then for of the, and so אבילות avelus
doesn't start until after the רגל, regel, and the time during the
רגל regel doesn't count towards the שבעה. shiva. Okay. And the reason
again that we said is because רגל regel is so much שמחה,
simcha, so much antithetical to the idea of אבילות, avelus, that you
can't have this period of שמחה simcha during the רגל regel count
towards שבעה. shiva. So the רגל regel does interrupt שבעה shiva because
the person was buried during the רגל, regel, okay, and the רגל
regel doesn't count towards it. So what's the גמרא's Gemara question? The
גמרא's Gemara question isn't about שבעה, shiva, the גמרא's Gemara question is
about
שלשים. shloshim. Person was buried during the רגל, regel, okay, and now
there's let's say, I don't know, four days left of יום טוב,
Yom Tov, okay, so the אבילות avelus really won't kick in until
after יום טוב Yom Tov because it was buried during the רגל,
regel, but do those four days at least count to deduct from
the total amount of time that have to observe שלשים? shloshim? Why
should, why should you be more able to deduct the time from
שלשים shloshim than you should from שבעה? shiva? So two reasons. One,
at the conceptual level, שבעה shiva is much more at a core
level, you know, antithetical to the idea of שבעה, shiva, which is
the most profound sense of אבילות. avelus. שלשים, shloshim, which is a
weaker sense of אבילות, avelus, I mean, okay, it countered to it
as well, but it's not like it's completely, maybe at some conceptual
level, completely incompatible. That's one issue, but the, and the practical issue
is, and this gets us to what this is doing in this
מסכתא, Masecheta, is that the exact practices of שלשים shloshim are ironically
observed by everybody during חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Because during חול המועד
Chol HaMoed you're not allowed to launder and, you know, get a
haircut. So maybe because those practices are observed somewhat ironically for very
different reason, you are allowed, that time can count towards the שלשים.
shloshim. So that is the question. The רגל regel doesn't count towards
שבעה, shiva, does it count towards שלשים? shloshim? And I want to
just jump ahead and tell you the הלכה. halacha. The הלכה halacha
is that it does, and that it does to such an extent
that if a person is let's say observed seven days before the
רגל regel and they're done with שבעה, shiva, and comes along the
רגל, regel, so the רגל regel now, oh well no that not
that case, the רגל regel wouldn't interrupt שלשים shloshim as it does
יום טוב. Yom Tov. The
person, somebody dies during the
רגל, regel, you have the what do you call it, you have,
so, so the רגל regel doesn't interrupt the שבעה, shiva, but the
days of the רגל regel do get deducted from the שלשים. shloshim.
And what becomes even more interesting is if it's during let's say
סוכות, Succos, and then I'm wondering whether I should tell you these
so complicated things, but it's just so fascinating. If it comes during
סוכות, Succos, so then when, when it hits שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeres,
which is considered its own רגל, regel, so since שלשים shloshim hasn't
yet really been observed, שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeres doesn't interrupt שלשים, shloshim,
but because it counts as its own רגל, regel, it deducts seven
more days from שלשים. shloshim. So days during the רגל regel actually,
and שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeres counts as like a punch of seven
days all by itself, do get deducted from שלשים, shloshim, although then
again it won't sort of deduct time from the actual observance of
שבעה. shiva. שבעה shiva will get observed afterwards, but the actual amount
of time of observing שלשים shloshim gets deducted as it were during
that period. And that's the גמרא's Gemara question here. Can the רגל
regel period count to take away time from the שלשים? shloshim? קברו
ברגל רגל עולה למנין שלשים או אין רגל עולה למנין שלשים? Kivaro
be'regel, regel oleh le'minyan shloshim o ein regel oleh le'minyan shloshim? למנין
שבעה לא קא מיבעיא לי. Le'minyan shiva lo ka mibaya li. I
don't have a question that it doesn't take away from שבעה, shiva,
if a person dies during the רגל regel you don't get to
do less for שבעה. shiva. דלא נהגא מצות שבעה ברגל, Delo nahaga
mitzvas shiva baregel, because שבעה shiva isn't practiced during the רגל. regel.
Any of the practices of שבעה shiva are not observed during the
רגל, regel, or the distinctive practices of שבעה, shiva, so there's no
way it could take, it could discount time at all or to
suggest that at a conceptual level it's so antithetical to the רגל
regel that it can't count. The רגל regel can't count towards שבעה.
shiva. But כי קא מיבעיא לי, ki ka mibaya li, my question
is למנין שלשים. le'minyan shloshim. Does the time during the רגל regel
count to deduct from שלשים? shloshim? דקא נהגא מצות שלשים ברגל, Dekanaga
mitzvas shloshim baregel, because ironically you do the main practices of שלשים
shloshim during the רגל: regel: not getting a haircut and not, and
not laundering clothes. So מאי, mai, what's the story? אמר ליה, Amar
lei, אינו עולה. eino oleh. So the initial response of רבה Rabba
was it doesn't count towards that. Does the time during the רגל
regel count to deduct from שלשים? shloshim? כנגד keneged מצות mitzat שלשים
shloshim ברגל, baregel, because ironically you do the main practices of שלשים
shloshim during the רגל: regel: not getting a haircut and not laundering
clothes. So מה? mah? What's the story? אמר ליה, amar lei, אינו
עולה. eino oleh. So the initial response of רבא Rava was: It
doesn't count towards that. You don't get to deduct that time. איתיביה,
eitivei, I'll ask you on this: הקובר מתו—so hakover meto we have
a תוספתא—somebody tosefta buries his relative שני ימים shnei yamim קודם הרגל,
kodem haregel, two days before, again with the assumption that less than
three days the רגל regel does not interrupt.
מונה חמישה ימים אחר רגל, moneh chamishah yamim achar regel, so you
have to, the person has to complete שבעה shiva after the רגל,
regel, five days after. Now, normally during שבעה shiva a person cannot
have work go out and do work or even have work done
for him. But in this case, where the five days after, you
know, the sort of seven days in, this is going to be
a funny middle position, because the שבעה shiva began before the רגל,
regel, so and the seven-day period ended during the רגל, regel, but
the practice is, the five extra days of practicing שבעה shiva get
postponed until after the רגל, regel, but the seven days from the
outset end during the רגל. regel. And the גמרא Gemara is going
to sort of split the difference in the following way: that things
that do have to do with the person's own practice gets done
in those five days after. Things that have to do with the
community's practice, like paying a שבעה shiva call, gets done sort of
during the initial seven days, which makes sense also because in terms
of the person's need for consolation and so on, once it started
before the רגל, regel, it would continue even during חול המועד. chol
hamoed. The interesting הלכה halacha is, is that even though there's not
practices of שבעה shiva during the רגל, regel, you can do ניחום,
nichum, you know, and you can do ניחום nichum on שבת Shabbos
and so on. It's a very interesting middle stage there. So, and
interestingly, the issue of doing מלאכה, melacha, which might have certain communal
aspects to it, what exactly is the problem with מלאכה? melacha? We
discussed before, so that actually, when in this case where it gets
interrupted, it's a
much weaker prohibition for the period after the רגל, regel, since it
started before and sort of ran during חול המועד chol hamoed as
well. So let's take a look at that. It says: So מונה
חמישה ימים אחר רגל, moneh chamishah yamim achar regel, five days have
to be completed after the רגל. regel. ומלאכתו נעשית על ידי אחרים.
umelachto naasit al yedei acherim. In this case, other people are allowed
to do, you know, you can have people do this person's work
for him. He doesn't do it himself after the רגל regel for
those five days, but he can actually have people, you know, workers
work for him. ועבדיו ושפחותיו עושים בצנעה בתוך ביתו. vaavadav veshifchotav osim
betzinah betoch beito. And if he has, you know, male, female servants,
they can actually do work in private inside the person's house. None
of this would be allowed during a normal שבעה, shiva, but in
this case about the postponed the five days, the extra days, then
it is, we're more lenient.
ואין רבים מתעסקין עמו. ve'ein rabim mitaskin imo. And during these extra
five, these postponed five days, the masses do not involve themselves with
him, meaning that there's no ניחום אבלים. nichum aveilim. Why?
שכבר נתעסקו בו ברגל. shekevar nitasku vo baregel. Because they already did
it during the רגל. regel. So again, a fascinating idea, right? That
you would think, like, if there's you don't do דברים שבפרהסיא devarim
shebefarhesya during the רגל. regel. If you don't do, you know, you
only do דברים שבצנעה devarim shebetzinah during the רגל, regel, you don't
have a public expression of mourning during the רגל, regel, it's fascinating
that people can still sort of say words of תנחומין, tanchumin, right?
It's public, right? That's the most public maybe form, that people are
sort of publicly acknowledging that. But on the other hand, you know,
there's a reality that that's when the person is most suffering and
in need of the תנחומין, tanchumin, even if you have the רגל
regel interrupting. So that takes place straight, and therefore the ניחום אבלים
nichum aveilim does not continue because that took place sort of, you
know, during the רגל, regel, but the practices are postponed for the
five days afterwards. Yeah.
Can you say more about this idea of people
practicing during חול המועד? chol hamoed?
I mean, like, why we allow that and don't allow the person
to do it himself, like, what's the split?
Or, what are the restrictions on it? Does the person run his
business? Is he talking about doing business?
No, they're talking more about running a business than about the types
of issues, I mean, that might have been what we were talking
about in חול המועד chol hamoed too, but certainly by אבילות aveilus
we're not talking at all about a concept of ל"ט מלאכות. lamed
tet melachos. We're talking about, like, sort of person involving himself in
his normal professional types of activities. And that partly has to do
as we sort of discussed before, you know, partly has to do
with this issue about distracting oneself from the אבילות, aveilus, and another
aspect has to do with the, you know, sort of the societal
integration aspects. And I think that that's what the split here is,
is that during these five days that have been postponed, right, so
the person is still supposed to do the practices, they personally can't
do the, go to work, you know, whatever or sit by their
computer, even if it's not leaving the house, because that's completely distracting
themselves from that mindset, but having other people work for a person,
which might have to do with the person, like, some certain integration
into society even if not personal, but you know, sort of getting
my work done, that is more allowed here, the same way that
there's, because sort of the societal aspects had sort of ended during
the שבעה shiva during the רגל, regel, the same way the ניחום
אבלים nichum aveilim ended during the רגל. regel.
In an un-postponed שבעה? shiva?
Then even other people are not supposed to work for, so what
does it mean like a person owns a business, what exactly are
the parameters of, yeah, that's an interesting question. It's less like the
שבת Shabbos idea, you know, about if you own a business, you
have to find a way to sell it. It's more like, you
know, I have to,
I'd have to... have to look into it a little more before
giving you an answer off the top of my head. But you
know, but it more has to do with taking care of my
personal responsibilities for me, rather than I've got a business and people
are, you know, are working in my employ. It has to do
more like you know, delegating some of your personal responsibilities.
So, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, וכל שהוא משום עסקי רבים אין רגל מפסיקו. V'chol shehu mishum
iskei rabim ein regel mafsiko. כל דבר
כל משום משום אבילות רגל מפסיקו. Kol davar kol mishum mishum aveilus
regel mafsiko. Anything that was related to the person's own observance of
אבילות aveilus was not practiced during the רגל, regel, וכל שהוא משום
עסקי רבים אין רגל מפסיקו, V'chol shehu mishum iskei rabim ein regel
mafsiko, but if it was about the practice of the community, that,
as I said, somewhat surprisingly, is not interrupted during the רגל regel
and the community would continue to do ניחום אבלים nichum aveilim during
that time. So that's in the case where we- we never have
this scenario nowadays because we פוסק posken even if a person began
it just one minute, the רגל regel interrupts, but if you needed
a minimum of three days, you could have an idea of two
days at the beginning and five days at the end and this
interesting middle period during the רגל regel where the person isn't doing
his own practices, but the community is doing their ניחום אבלים. nichum
aveilim. One minute, קברו שלושה ימים. kvaro shlosha yamim. If he did
three days, right, בסוף הרגל, besof ha'regel, not before the רגל, regel,
during the רגל, regel, like in the last three days during in
חול המועד Chol HaMoed this person was buried, so in that case
מונה שבעה אחר הרגל. moneh shiva achar ha'regel. The whole שבעה shiva
is postponed until after the רגל. regel. ארבעה ימים הראשונים, Arba'ah yamim
ha'rishonim, now, the only relevance here, I mean the whole person's אבילות
aveilus was postponed till after the רגל. regel. Ah, but remember the
community starts to do their practices regardless of רגל regel based on
after the burial. So even if the person didn't even begin his
practice before the רגל, regel, the community would begin their ניחום אבלים
nichum aveilim immediately after the person was buried. So the last four-
the first four days following the רגל, regel, רבים מתעסקים בו. rabim
misaskim bo. The community continues to involve themselves with him and do
ניחום אבלים. nichum aveilim. שלושה ימים האחרונים, Shlosha yamim ha'achronim, the last
three days of the שבעה shiva following the רגל, regel, אין רבים
מתעסקין בו שכבר נתעסקו בו
ברגל. ein rabim misaskin bo she'kvar nisasku bo ba'regel. So they don't
continue to do ניחום אבלים nichum aveilim because they already began in
the רגל. regel. So again, this is quite shocking I think, right?
Because we certainly don't have a concept of like, you know, it's
one thing you see somebody who's in אבילות aveilus during שבת Shabbos
or during the רגל regel and you say a few words to
the person, but the idea that everybody would like go and as
a community and pay a שבעה shiva call during שבת Shabbos or
during the רגל, regel, you know, like in our mind again, what
more פרהסיא parhesia do you want than something like that? But what-
yeah, I mean not to the degree that the גמרא Gemara I
think the phrase רבים מתעסקים, rabim misaskim, you know, suggests a large
type of a communal presence. It's to me it's quite shocking that
that you can sort of that you do during the רגל, regel,
but on the one hand, it's very, you know, you know, it's
really profound because whether that you're telling the אבל ovel to do
certain practices or not, you know, that they should feel like abandoned
right after this time that nobody is actually, you know, speaking words
of consolation, reaching out to them and so on. And here it
says that regardless of the רגל, regel, that takes place seven days
following burial, even if the burial was during the רגל, regel, the
burial was before but the practices were postponed, the רבים's rabim sort
of involvement is seven days following the burial, even if in this
case the whole practice is postponed till much afterwards. Okay, so that's
that case.
One minute, let's finish this.
מונה שבעה
אחר הרגל. Moneh shiva achar ha'regel. ואימתי ומה ואימתי ורגל עולה לו.
V'eimasai v'ma v'eimasai v'regel oleh lo. Okay, sorry, sorry. ורגל עולה לו.
V'regel oleh lo. Okay, so in this case of someone who's buried
during the רגל, regel, it says ורגל עולה לו. v'regel oleh lo.
Now what's it counting towards?
If the whole practices were postponed till after the רגל regel in
the case of a burial on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, what is
the רגל regel counting for? It can't be for שבעה, shiva, that's
clear, the משנה Mishnah says the רגל regel doesn't עולה. oleh. So
it sounds like those days count to deduct from שלושים. shloshim. מאי
לאו אסיפא, Mai lav asseifa, isn't this going on the second case
where the person was buried during the רגל regel and it says
that the רגל regel counts to deduct from שלושים? shloshim? גמרא Gemara
says לא ארישא, lo areisha, not necessarily. Maybe when it says the
רגל regel counts, it was the first case, two days before the
רגל. regel. And in that scenario when a person actually began their
practice before the רגל, regel, then they'll concede that the period during
the רגל regel deducts from שלושים. shloshim. But if the person was
buried during the רגל, regel, maybe everything gets so much postponed that
like nothing starts during the רגל regel itself. I want to remind
people though that even though it might not get discounted, the הלכה
halacha still is that if somebody has a burial on חול המועד,
Chol HaMoed, they still practice דברים שבצנעא. devarim she'betzina. They still don't
do you know those אבילות aveilus practices that are private are still
observed, which is like bathing and sex and so on. So it's
not like everything really gets postponed. There are some practice- private practice
that gets done, but the גמרא Gemara is saying whether you can
count against שלושים, shloshim, maybe it needs to have started ahead of
time. So the גמרא Gemara still hasn't resolved. We are going to
conclude as I said in a minute that even when the death
is during the רגל regel and it sounds like everything is being
postponed Yes, so in a מצב של, matzav shel, or how would
you say, is it appropriate then to say personal words? Even though...
I was wondering if it
would bring them away from their being
involved
with שבת. Shabbos.
I know, it is funny. You know, that actually is the הלכה
Halacha and it's because that you do can do ניחום אבלים nichum
aveilim on שבת. Shabbos. And you know, we all do this thing
that before, you know, before שבת Shabbos begins, we welcome the אבלים,
aveilim, המקום ינחם אתכם, HaMakom yenachem etchem, which sets the... sets the...
sets the message, you know, that it's like I mean, you know,
seems to be setting the message that it's you're doing it before
שבת. Shabbos. Of course you just did לכה דודי, Lecha Dodi, בואי
כלה בואי כלה Boee kallah boee kallah which is קבלת שבת, Kabbalat
Shabbos,
and you are saying המקום ינחם אתכם. HaMakom yenachem etchem. So if
you think about it, you really are doing ניחום אבלים nichum aveilim
on שבת, Shabbos, right? You just were מקבל שבת. mekabel Shabbos. And
most of the times, depending on which שול shul you go to,
a lot of the time by the time they get up to
לכה דודי Lecha Dodi anyway, it's already you know dark and it's
already sunset. So actually, but somehow the message gets communicated, I think
you know, the impression gets communicated that we're doing that before שבת
Shabbos and we're not going to do it on שבת, Shabbos, but
the actual הלכה Halacha is you do ניחום אבלים nichum aveilim on
שבת. Shabbos.
Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, where were we?
Okay.
מיתיבי? Meitivei? No. So I'll ask you another from another ברייתא. Braita.
רגל עולה לו למנין שלושים. Regel oleh lo leminyan Shloshim. רגל Regel
counts towards שלושים. Shloshim. Here's an explicit ברייתא. Braita. כיצד? Keitzad? קברו
בתחילת הרגל, Kavro betchilat haRegel, if a person was buried at the
beginning of the רגל, Regel, מונה שבעה אחר הרגל, Moneh shiva achar
haRegel, so again, assuming you need three days, so the whole שבעה
shiva is done after the רגל. Regel. ומלאכתו נעשית על ידי אחרים,
Umlachto naasit al yedei acherim, and again,
because you know, the immediate period following the שבעה, shiva, following the
burial even if it's a רגל Regel is one where you have
the ניחום אבלים nichum aveilim of the masses and where the more
intense prohibitions of מלאכה melacha apply. So in this case where it
got postponed, the שבעה shiva that's observed after the רגל, Regel, work
can be done for this person by other people. ועבדיו ושפחותיו עושים
בצנעה בתוך ביתו, Vaavadav veshifchotav osim betzinah betoch beito, so and his
servants can work in the house in private. ואין רבים מתעסקים בו,
Veein rabbim mitaskim bo, and again, in this period that was postponed,
the masses would not continue to involve themselves to do שבעה, shiva,
שכבר נתעסקו בו ברגל, Shekevar nitasku bo baRegel, they did it during
the רגל, Regel, they did the ניחום אבלים nichum aveilim during the
רגל. Regel. Okay, so all of that fine, we've seen that idea
about postponement, but here's now the kicker: ורגל עולה לו, VeRegel oleh
lo, and the רגל Regel counts. Okay, so it says that the
רגל Regel counts, and this is a case where now, it's... I'm
sorry, I misread the case. I said בתחילת הרגל, betchilat haRegel, I
said right before the רגל, Regel, but it's actually בתחילת הרגל betchilat
haRegel meaning during the רגל. Regel. I'm sorry. So it was a
burial during the רגל, Regel, everything got postponed, and even though everything
got postponed and it was a burial during the רגל, Regel, it
says the רגל Regel counts. So you see that
even if a burial during the רגל, Regel, the time of the
רגל Regel counts to deduct from שלושים. Shloshim. And the גמרא Gemara
says תיופתא, Tiyufta, that's right, that is a contradiction to רבא's Rava
assertion. We see that the רגל Regel does count to deduct from
שלושים Shloshim even for a burial during the רגל. Regel. כי אתא
רבין אמר אמר רבי יוחנן, Ki ata Ravin amar amar Rabbi Yochanan,
אפילו קברו ברגל, Afilu kavro baRegel,
and not only do you have a ברייתא, Braita, we have a
teaching of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, even if somebody was buried during
the רגל, Regel, the period of the רגל Regel counts to deduct
from שלושים. Shloshim. וכן אורי ליה רבי אלעזר לרבי פדת בריה, Vechen
uri lei Rabbi Elazar leRabbi Pedat breh, רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar so
said this to רבי פדת's Rabbi Pedat son. אפילו קברו ברגל, Afilu
kavro baRegel, even a burial during the רגל, Regel, the רגל Regel
is deducted... the time of the רגל Regel deducts from שלושים. Shloshim.
That is the הלכה Halacha and as I said, it becomes even
more bizarre when you get to the issue of שמיני עצרת, Shemini
Atzeret, which counts for a whole seven days, just that one day.
Yes. Did אביי Abaye just win an argument with רבא? Rava?
Well, they switched gears to רבא, Rava, but that could be. Anyway,
that does happen every now and then.
Okay? Right...
I don't remember this as one of the six cases.
Right. Right, okay, yeah, but that's true, but here he was actually
beaten. Now let me give you the following scenario, okay? Somebody buries
somebody a minute before
סוכות, Sukkot, an hour before סוכות, Sukkot, ערב סוכות. erev Sukkot. So
comes along סוכות Sukkot and they're done with שבעה. shiva. Okay, now.
So how many days are left of שלושים Shloshim to be observed?
23, because that's
the הלכה, Halacha, you should sort of treat the first seven as
the whole, you know, it sets... you don't get 30 outside of
the seven. So a person's left with 23. Now there's the רגל.
Regel. So that whole seven days of סוכות Sukkot gets deducted, so
the person only has 16 days of שלושים Shloshim left. Comes שמיני
עצרת, Shemini Atzeret, we deduct another seven days. After the רגל, Regel,
the person only observes nine days of שלושים. Shloshim. So it's quite
fascinating, this הלכה Halacha plus the שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret sort of
trick can get the scenario of a burial before סוכות Sukkot that
only nine days left. But even in the non-סוכות Sukkot scenario, even
like a פסח Pesach scenario, a person is buried before פסח, Pesach,
then comes along... then what like you know, ערב פסח erev Pesach
somebody's buried, comes פסח, Pesach, no more שבעה, shiva, left with 23
days, comes פסח, Pesach, deduct another seven days. and after פסח Pesach
even though there's no real observance of שלשים Shloshim during פסח. Pesach.
I mean, okay, there's no laundry and there's no haircut because of
חול המועד, Chol Hamoed, right? That's the whole point, right? But anyway,
but the separate but after פסח Pesach there will only be 16
days of שלשים Shloshim left to be observed. That actually is the
הלכה. Halacha.
There's interesting questions of what the role of יום טוב שני Yom
Tov Sheni is and so on, but anyway, but this is the
הלכה Halacha about deducting this period from the observance of שלשים. Shloshim.
Okay, so that's actually how we פוסקן. Pasken. Now, if somebody dies
during the רגל, Regel, it's much less of an importation. שבעה Shiva
doesn't get annulled. Since שבעה Shiva doesn't get annulled, you start with
the, the person starts with the full complement of 30 days. So
if the, if there were like four days left of יום טוב
Yomtov when somebody dies חול המועד, Chol Hamoed, there was four days
left, so afterwards, fine, person has 26 days left of observing, right?
But that's a lot, the impact is a lot less because the
whole full seven still remains. But when it was beforehand, the רגל
Regel first got away of שבעה Shiva and the seven of the
30, and then plus the רגל Regel gets away with another seven
or more of that.
Doesn't it stop the, doesn't it stop the seven days of שבעה
Shiva when death occurs
during the רגל?
Regel? Death during the רגל Regel it, oh, that's interesting. Right, you're
right, you're right, you're right. So the שבעה Shiva is observed after.
Does the, you know what, it might. I'll have to double-check that.
Don't remember off the top of my head. I'll have to double-check
that. Okay, so let's take a look. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Now
we are going to get to finally challenging this idea that it
needs to be three days before the רגל Regel and get to
our practice. אם כפיית המטה שלשה ימים קודם הרגל. Im kefiyat hamitah
shlosha yamim kodem haregel. If a person observed the upturning of the
bed, interesting why it focuses on this, because this is one of
the more, there's a fascinating question in general about practices of אבילות,
Avelus, whether you view them as לא תעשה's Lo Ta'aseh or עשה's,
Aseh right? Meaning how much do you sort of say a person
isn't allowed to bathe, they're not allowed to wear shoes, so it's
like things that you're not doing, or how much do you view
them as visible practices and demonstrations of אבילות. Avelus. This is what
it means to demonstrate אבילות, Avelus, to go around barefoot,
unshaved, on un-haircutted or whatever. So one of the things that's clearly
a עשה Aseh if you would, not a לא תעשה, Lo Ta'aseh,
a demonstrative practice, is this upturning of the bed. It's not denying
things to yourself, it's actually actively doing something that demonstrates אבילות. Avelus.
So sometimes that is used as sort of as
an example as like a paradigm, as a key as of what
it means to do practices of אבילות, Avelus, which is interesting. Why
choose כפיית המטה Kefiyat hamitah over everything else? But as we've seen
elsewhere, we're familiar with some of these other things to see them
more as like restrictions, whereas this is really seen, but those other
things do have both elements, this clearly is something that's seen as
an observance. So that's why it's given here as an example probably.
If a person observed the upturning of the bed three days before
the רגל, Regel, אינו צריך לכפותו אחר הרגל. Eino tzarich likfoso achar
haregel. So then the רגל Regel it's a way of saying three
days of observance of שבעה, Shiva, so then the רגל Regel is
מבטל Mevatel the שבעה Shiva based, like our משנה. Mishna. דברי רבי
אליעזר. Divrei Rabbi Eliezer. That's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says. וחכמים
אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, and this is our position, אפילו יום אחד, Afilu
yom echad, even one day is enough that the רגל Regel will
interrupt it. אפילו שעה אחת, Afilu sha'ah achas, even one hour. Burial
one hour before יום טוב, Yomtov, 10 minutes before יום טוב, Yomtov,
as long, the יום טוב Yomtov comes and is מבטל Mevatel the
שבעה. Shiva. אמר רבי אלעזר בר רבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi Elazar bar
Rabbi Shimon, הן הן דברי בית שמאי הן הן דברי בית הלל.
Hen hen divrei Beis Shammai hen hen divrei Beis Hillel. This actually
is the debate between בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל. Beis
Hillel. שבית שמאי אומרים שלשה ימים ובית הלל אומרים אפילו יום אחד.
She-Beis Shammai omrim shlosha yamim u-Beis Hillel omrim afilu yom echad. בית
שמאי Beis Shammai says three and בית הלל Beis Hillel says even
one, which is quite fascinating because all of the תנאי Tannaitic material
until now had said three. So all of that has been influenced
by בית שמאי? Beis Shammai? It's not one of these like bizarre,
like completely rejected opinions. It seems like there actually was a pretty
dominant strand of three days. But now that it's being identified with
בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, we know where things are going. אמר רב
הונא אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן ואמרי לה אמר
רבי יוחנן לרבי חייא בר אבא או רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna
amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan ve-amri lah amar Rabbi
Yochanan l'Rabbi Chiya bar Abba o Rav Huna, אפילו יום אחד אפילו
שעה אחת. Afilu yom echad afilu sha'ah achas. Again, even one day,
even one hour, again רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is being מיקל. Meikel.
We just had a מיקל Meikel before about a burial during the
רגל. Regel. Even one hour is enough to interrupt שבעה. Shiva. רבא
אמר. Rava amar. Now רבא Rava says, הלכה כתנא דידן. Halacha ke-tana
didan. We follow our תנא. Tanna. דאמר שלשה. De-amar shlosha. You need
three. So again fascinating, because based on the גרסא Gersa before, רבה
Rabbah or רבא, Rava, רבא Rava is coming out again more strict
and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan more lenient. One wonders is it possible
there were בבל Bavel and ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael differences about this?
I don't know, I haven't completely tracked that. But anyway, again we
see these differences. דאמר שלשה. De-amar shlosha. Now, רבינא איקלע לסורא דפרת.
Ravina ikla l'Sura d'Peras. רבינא Ravina came to סורא Sura by the
פרת. Perat. So this is בבל. Bavel. אמר ליה רב חביבא לרבינא,
Amar lei Rav Chaviva l'Ravina, הלכתא מאי? Hilchasa mai? What's the הלכה?
Halacha? אמר ליה אפילו יום אחד אפילו שעה אחת. Amar lei afilu
yom echad afilu sha'ah achas.
So here רבינא Ravina is being lenient, even one day, even one
hour is enough for שלשים Shloshim to be, for רגל Regel to
be מבטל Mevatel it. יתבי רבי חייא בר אבא ורבי אמי ורבי
יצחק נפחא. Yasvi Rabbi Chiya bar Abba v'Rabbi Ami v'Rabbi Yitzchak Napcha.
So these three rabbis were sitting. אקילעא דרבי יצחק בן אלעזר. A-kila
d'Rabbi Yitzchak ben Elazar. On the porch of רבי יצחק בן אלעזר.
Rabbi Yitzchak ben Elazar. נפק מילתא בינייהו. Nafak milsa beinaihu. And
a word emerged from them, I mean, they all of, a consensus
came from them, מניין לאבילות שבעה? Minayin l'avelus shiva? Where do you
know the idea of אבילות aveilus for seven days? דכתיב: Dichsiv: והפכתי
חגיכם לאבל. V'hafachti chageichem l'eivel.
I will turn your your holiday into a mourning. מה חג שבעה
Ma chag shiva the same way a standard חג chag is seven
days, אף אבילות שבעה, af aveilus shiva, אבילות aveilus is seven days.
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, ואימא עצרת דחד יומא? v'eima
atzeret d'chad yoma? One minute, there's שבועות, Shavuos, it's a one-day חג.
chag. No, ההוא מיבעי ליה לכדריש לקיש. hahu mibayei lei l'che'd'Resh Lakish.
That,
there is an idea of a one-day אבילות aveilus for what ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish teaches. דאמר ריש לקיש D'amar Resh Lakish because ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish teaches משום רבי יהודה נשיאה mishum Rabbi Yehuda Nesia
in the name of רבי יהודה נשיאה, Rabbi Yehuda Nesia, the grandson
of רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi, מניין לשמועה רחוקה שאינו נוהג
אלא יום אחד? Minayin l'shmua rechoka she'eino noheig ella yom echad? How
do you know that if somebody hears a distant report, distant in
time, meaning hears a report much after the person has passed away?
Right, this happens sometimes, you know, that somebody hears only like a
long time later that a brother died. I mean, even now with
instant communication, sometimes family members feel it's not appropriate to let somebody
know. There's, anyway, this thing happens. Certainly in those times when communications
were not instantaneous. So a person hears only much after the death.
So if it's a long time after, which we'll define in a
minute, then there's only one day of אבילות aveilus because it's the
sense of the immediacy, you know, although it's quite interesting from the
person's subjective perspective it's immediate, but nevertheless, you know, it gets also
to interesting questions about how much is practices of אבילות aveilus for
the sake of the observer or for the sake of the person
who has passed away, you know, and to honor the person who
has passed away. So if it's a distance from the observer's perspective,
the subjective perspective, you know, what if there's still immediate, they just
found out? But nevertheless, the distance from the actual death means that,
and maybe even the person is aware how distant it is, that
impacts their own sense of, you know, about of their psychological state.
So the practice is that the אבילות aveilus therefore is practiced much
less and only practiced one day. דכתיב, Dichsiv, how do you know
this? והפכתי חגיכם לאבל. V'hafachti chageichem l'eivel. Okay, ואשכחן עצרת דאיקרי חג
יומא. v'ashkechan atzeret d'ikri chag yoma.
So your, so this idea, your חג chag will be an אבל
evel and שבועות Shavuos is only one day. So there's a sense
of an אבילות aveilus that's one day in this case when it
is after a long period after the death. So that's the, that's
what we get the seven days and that's where we get a
case of a one day. Now, just for a moment to recognize
that it's very fascinating to quote this verse, since in the תורה
Torah you often get discussions of seven days אבילות aveilus and so
on, right? So look at תוספות. Tosafot. He says מה חג שבעה.
Ma chag shiva.
So he says בירושלמי דייק, B'Yerushalmi dayek, ואימא שמונה כשמונה דחג? v'eima
shmona k'shmona d'chag? How about the eight days of סוכות? Succos? ומשני
שמיני רגל בפני עצמו הוא. u'meshani shmini regel bifnei atzmo hu. שמיני
עצרת Shmini Atzeret is its own יום טוב, Yom Tov, which has
implications as I just told you for counting against the
שלושים. shloshim. ויעש לאביו אבל שבעת ימים? U'mi-yas l'aviv eivel shivat yamim?
How about the death of יעקב? Yaakov? And that they said they
observed an אבל evel for seven days, right? לא מצית לאסויי דהתם
קודם קבורה הויה. Lo matzit l'asuyei d'hasam kodem kevura havaya. That was
not real הלכתי halachic אבילות, aveilus, that was before they buried יעקב.
Yaakov. So okay, but still shows practice, I mean, you know, how
about when משה Moshe and אהרן Aharon died, right? You get the
idea of, of thirty days. None of those narratives are being used,
although clearly those practices were there. Also the idea, by the way,
of like the שבע ברכות sheva brachos and the seven days after
the wedding, you get that from the stories with יעקב Yaakov and
רחל ולאה, Rachel v'Leah, מלא שבוע זאת malei shavua zos and so
on. So you know, there clearly is the idea that these institutions
were around way earlier, but it's interesting what the גמרא Gemara is
choosing to use as a model for the הלכתי halachic practice. And
and here he says ובירושלמי משני דאין למידין מקודם מתן תורה. u'v'Yerushalmi
meshani d'ein l'meidin mikodem mattan torah. והתם בירושלמי מייתי קראי טובא. v'hasam
b'Yerushalmi mayisi kra'ei tuva. Oh, you can't learn from before מתן תורה.
mattan torah. But anyway, it is fascinating, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi has many
sources. It is fascinating the limited sources the גמרא Gemara has here,
also the limited source for you know, שלושים shloshim from the case
of the נזיר nazir when there clearly are practices in the תורה
Torah about שבעה shiva and שלושים shloshim and so on. So I
don't really have an answer, but תוספות Tosafot at least raises the
the issue and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi has many other sources. Yes.
How could anyone even suggest that the death of יעקב אבינו Yaakov
Avinu be a model? He was embalmed.
Well, yes. Okay. Well, that's exactly what the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says. But
nevertheless, it certainly reflects a reality that there was a sense, even
if it wasn't done הלכתית, halachically, that there was a period of
mourning of a week and so on. I think the רמב"ם, Rambam,
if I can find it very quickly, let me see, I might,
if if I can find it very quickly, I won't do it.
The רמב"ם Rambam specifically relates to some of these narratives. Hold on.
But while you're looking, I have another. Yes. We do derive some
before מתן תורה, mattan torah, such as הכנסת אורחים. hachnasat orchim. What?
From אברהם אבינו. Avraham Avinu.
Yeah, again, what we choose to do to derive and not derive,
it's all very arbitrary. So, I mean, this issue of לפני מתן
תורה. lifnei mattan torah.
So, yeah, I'm not... Yes.
What?
Hold on, let me just see. I'm not, yeah, I'm not finding
it.
Okay.
Okay, I'll look for I'll find I'll find a few for tomorrow.
I'm not finding it right now. Okay.
But as you read this just as a naive user, yes, it
sounds like maybe there was an established practice of 30 days, 7
days, as we find. Right. And then the fact that there's so
little sources being cited as this conversation goes, yes, it sounds like
they're talking about, okay, so how do we observe those 30 days?
What's the structure we're going to put around it?
But the sources aren't where do you know the practices. That was
a discussion much earlier in מסכת מועד קטן. Masechet Moed Katan. Remember?
How do you know that an אבל avel can't do this? How
do you know an אבל avel can't do this? How do you
know an אבל avel can't do this?
But then when you're talking about, okay, so now you're in this
special circumstance where you have שמועה קרובה. shemu'ah kerovah. Right. Right. And
it, I don't know, to this naive reader, yes, it feels like
they're schmoozing, okay, so we know this general practice is going to
happen. Right. What do we do when we have this circumstance? And
they're saying, you know what, here's what it feels like it should
be. What, what's the legal, here's some spiritual guidance as to how
you, how you should do it. And it, it really does feel
like this.
Well, I mean it is worth saying by the way that the
whole debate in the ראשונים Rishonim is about whether day one is
דאורייתא. de'Oraita. Everybody agrees that beyond day one it's all Rabbinic. So,
you know, so even though it's saying where do you know and
where do you know and so on, like it's completely agreed by
the ראשונים Rishonim that it's all Rabbinic after day one. At most
day one is the only thing that's דאורייתא. de'Oraita. So it also
raises right this question about where we're looking here is the source.
Okay, I'll find the רמב״ם Rambam for you later. But okay, let's
take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues.
תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: שמועה קרובה, Shemu'ah kerovah, now that we mentioned
this idea of שמועה רחוקה, shemu'ah rechokah, we're going to deal with
this הלכה. halachah. Here in the report like soon after and a
long time after. שמועה קרובה נוהגת שבעה ושלשים, Shemu'ah kerovah noheget shivah
u'shloshim, hearing a report soon after the death, the person observes שבעה
ושלשים, shivah u'shloshim. meaning the full
אבילות. aveilus. שמועה רחוקה אינה נוהגת אלא יום אחד Shemu'ah rechokah eino
noheget ella yom echad is one day. איזו היא קרובה ואיזו היא
רחוקה, Eizu hi kerovah v'eizu hi rechokah, what's the difference? קרובה בתוך
שלשים, Kerovah betoch shloshim, קרובה kerovah is within 30 days. רחוקה לאחר
שלשים. Rechokah le'achar shloshim. דברי רבי עקיבא, Divrei Rabbi Akiva, that's what
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. 30 days determine. וחכמים אומרים אחד שמועה
קרובה ואחד שמועה רחוקה נוהגת שבעה ושלשים. V'Chachamim omrim: achad shemu'ah kerovah
v'echad shemu'ah rechokah noheget shivah u'shloshim. Doesn't matter from the person's subjective
experience, they're just finding out about it, they're now experiencing the death,
so that they observe the entire שבעה ושלשים. shiva u'shloshim, Again, fascinating
I think in terms of what the whole point of the אבילות
aveilus is, right? Why from a subjective experience is it different? Maybe
it is different if it's a long time afterwards, but again from
everybody else's awareness of it, the community's awareness, the relationship to the
dead person and so on, those things are different. אמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן כל מקום שאתה מוצא יחיד מיקל, Amar
Rabbah bar bar Chana Amar Rabbi Yochanan: Kol makom she'atah motze yachid
meikel, and here's a very important principle that I've already told you
about, whenever you find a single opinion that's being lenient, ורבים מחמירים
v'rabim machmirim and the majority that's strict, הלכה כרבים, halachah k'rabim, we
go like the majority. חוץ מזו, Chutz mizu, with the exception of
this case here about whether you do... what you do by a
שמועה רחוקה, shemu'ah rechokah, שאף על פי שרבי עקיבא מיקל, she'af al
pi she'Rabbi Akiva meikel, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is a single opinion
and he's being lenient and says there's an idea of שמועה רחוקה
shemu'ah rechokah of only one day, וחכמים מחמירים v'Chachamim machmirim and the
חכמים Chachamim are strict, הלכה כרבי עקיבא, halachah k'Rabbi Akiva, we rule
like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. We rule that there's an idea of
only one day. דאמר שמואל הלכה כדברי המיקל באבל. De'amar Shmuel halachah
k'divrei hameikel b'avel. We go like the lenient position by אבל avel
and this is a very dominant thing that applies even till today
when there're מחלוקות machlokot about various things, principle that we always sort
of look for the more lenient opinion by אבל. avel. Now, it
could be because like I said it's דרבנן, derabbanan, you know, but
okay, we don't, we still say it in a much more
thoroughgoing way by הלכות אבילות hilchos aveilus than we say by other
דרבנן. derabbanans. Like here, even if something's a דרבנן, derabbanan, if it's
usually like a דעת יחיד da'as yachid against a רבים, rabim, we'll
usually go by the majority opinion, even by a דרבנן derabbanan we
won't always adopt the lenient. But by אבילות aveilus we tend to
do that, again, maybe with an understanding that all, you know, that
it's on the one hand, you know, observing of הלכות אבילות hilchos
aveilus is very helpful for somebody in that period of time. I
mean and many, many people find that, even who don't, you know,
do other areas of הלכה, halachah, how powerful it is to observe
הלכות אבילות. hilchos aveilus. And at the other hand, like, you know,
maybe it doesn't mean you have to, there has to be some
balance, it's also very demanding, and so we, so it is interesting
this idea that we always look for the lenient opinion by אבילות.
aveilus. Okay, and now we continue with this idea of שמועה רחוקה.
shemu'ah rechokah. רבי חנינא אתיא ליה שמועה דאבוהי מבי חוזאי. Rabbi Chanina
atya lei shemu'ah d'avuhi miBe Chuzai. רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina heard a
report about his father who was in מבי חוזאי Be Chuzai that
his father had passed away. אתא לקמיה דרב חסדא, Ata lekamei d'Rav
Chisda, he came to רב חסדא Rav Chisda and asked him how
much, what he should practice. אמר ליה שמועה רחוקה אינה נוהגת אלא
יום אחד. Amar lei: Shemu'ah rechokah eino noheget ella yom echad. It
was for a while since he
died, only one day of observance. רב נתן בר אמי אתיא ליה
שמועה דאמיה מבי חוזאי. Rav Natan bar Ami atya lei shemu'ah d'imei
miBe Chuzai. He heard a report about his mother's death in מבי
חוזאי. Be Chuzai. אתא לקמיה דרבא. Ata lekamei d'Rava. אמר ליה הרי
אמרו שמועה רחוקה אינה נוהגת אלא יום אחד, Amar lei: Harei amru
shemu'ah rechokah eino noheget ella yom echad, only one day observance. בלבד.
Bilvad. איתיבי, Eiseivi, says the גמרא Gemara asks on this, במה דברים
אמורים, bameh devarim amurim, when do we say one day of observance
for a שמועה רחוקה, shemu'ah rechokah, בחמשה... be-chamishah... Mother, father, brother, sister,
son, daughter, and wife. Okay, all of those are mentioned by the...
what? Spouse.
Whoops, sorry. Thank you very much.
If
Mira were still here, I would have really gotten it for that
one. Oh well. I'm just reflecting the whole male bias of this
text, but I should not be doing that. I'm sorry. Oh man.
But the reason, the one that's not, all of those are mentioned
by the כהן Kohen with the exception of spouse. Okay, actually by
כהן, Kohen, here's my, here's my defense, because it's based on who
a כהן Kohen is מטמא mitamei to, and that's only the male
כהן Kohen that actually is where we get it as the basis.
But what's interesting is the first six are mentioned that the כהן
Kohen is מטמא mitamei to. The כהן's Kohen wife, and here I
do mean wife, is not mentioned in the text. Actually, the פשט
pshat of the text says that a כהן Kohen is not מטמא
mitamei to his wife. לא יטמא בעל בעמיו. lo yitama ba'al b'amov.
What does, you know, so בעל ba'al might not mean husband, it
might mean something else, a prince among the people. Anyway, the Rabbis
though read into that text that a כהן Kohen is מטמא, mitamei,
understand his wife. It's actually a מחלוקת machlokes רמב״ם Rambam ראב״ד, Ra'avad,
meaning if his wife dies, he is allowed to come in contact
with his wife to bury her and take care of her and
so on. And because there, the idea that it overrides the prohibition
of a כהן Kohen becoming טמא tamei to take care of these
relatives that have died, that serves as the basis for us for
the idea of אבילות. aveilus. These are the people that a person
is responsible for in their death, and that becomes the basis of
אבילות. aveilus. There's an interesting debate of רמב״ם Rambam and ראב״ד Ra'avad
whether the fact that a כהן Kohen violates his טומאה tumah for
the sake of his wife is a biblical idea or rabbinic. According
to רמב״ם, Rambam, even though it's a דאורייתא de'oraisa prohibition of a
כהן Kohen becoming טמא, tamei, really it's the Rabbis created that and
said that a כהן Kohen overrides, they made his wife like a
מת מצוה meis mitzvah and so on. So anyway, but that is
the source of the seven people for whom somebody will sit שבעה.
shivah And what the גמרא's Gemara saying here is, it's putting out
a position that only five of them, not including, meaning not mother
and father, would we have this principle of שמועה רחוקה. shmuah rechokah.
Only for the five. אבל על אביו ועל אמו, aval al aviv
v'al imo, but mother and father, in that, שבעה ושלושים. shiva v'shloshim.
Just out of either the impact of the death or the issue
of respect for the parents, that is always going to demand a
full שבעה shiva. and שלושים. shloshim. It should be said right now
at this moment, by the way, and people do find it very
challenging that if you think like whose death is the hardest on
somebody, it's חס ושלום chas v'shalom there would be a death of
a child, right? Because that's not the normal way of the world.
You know, you expect the parents to die before the children. And
nevertheless,
for a person's parent, it's a whole idea of a year. So
it's important to understand that that's framed not as the sense of
like that death is harder than another death, but the aspect of
כיבוד אב ואם. kibbud av v'eim. That the idea of the י״ב
חודש yud beis chodesh is very much framed more in terms of
the כיבוד אב ואם kibbud av v'eim and not so much in
terms of, not saying that death isn't hard, but it's hard for
the other relatives as well. It's hard if a spouse dies also,
you know, that
from what I, from many people, is harder than when a parent
dies, especially if a parent is dying at sort of the natural
causes and later in life and so on. The spouse is the
person, God willing, of a happy marriage, the person that really feels
like part of the person in a much more profound way. And
nevertheless, by the parent it's twelve months because of the idea of
כיבוד אב ואם. kibbud av v'eim. So that's important to keep in
mind. So here the גמרא's Gemara saying that there's a full שבעה
shiva and שלושים shloshim by a שמועה רחוקה, shmuah rechokah, it probably
has less to do with the fact of like, oh this hits
a person more powerfully, and more because of the aspect of כיבוד
אב ואם. kibbud av v'eim. Yes.
Yes, it showed me it's very common.
That is true.
You know, up until
the 20th century, that is true. You know, but also question about
when is child dying, like in the early years that was more
common, right? But you have an adult parent and an adult
child. Anyway, so that's what this ברייתא baraisa is saying. So let's
see, and here was the case of a parent, so why are
you only saying one day? So the גמרא Gemara says the following.
Where was it? איתיביה, eisiveih, I asked on this. במה דברים אמורים,
bameh devarim amurim, בחמישה מתי מצוה, bachamishah meisei mitzvah, אבל על אביו
ועל אמו שבעה ושלושים. aval al aviv v'al imo shiva v'shloshim. אמר
ליה, amar leih, so he said back, יחידה היא, yechidah hi, that
ברייתא baraisa that says for parents you always do שבעה ושלושים, shiva
v'shloshim, that's a דעת יחיד. da'at yachid. That's a minority opinion, ולא
סבירא לן כוותיה, v'lo svira lan k'vasei, we don't rule like it.
דתניא, detanya, here's a ברייתא baraisa that you'll see that opinion, and
you'll see that it's a minority opinion. Let's see the ברייתא. baraisa.
מעשה ומת אביו של רבי צדוק בגינזק. ma'aseh u'meis aviv shel Rabi
Tzadok b'Ginzak. The father of רבי צדוק Rabi Tzadok died in גינזק,
Ginzak, והודיעו לאחר שלוש שנים. v'hodi'u achar shalosh shanim. And they told
him after three years, so that was clearly a שמועה רחוקה. shmuah
rechokah. ובא ושאל את אלישע בן אבויה. u'va v'sha'al es Elisha ben
Avuya. There's got to be one of the few texts where אלישע
בן אבויה Elisha ben Avuya is referred to right... by name as
a halachic authority, והזקנים שעמו V'hazkeinim she'imo and the elders with him,
but clearly he was the senior authority, he's the one that's named.
ואמרו V'omru and he said, No, שבעה ושלשים, shiva u'shloshim. you have
to do a full שבעה ושלשים. shiva u'shloshim. וכשמת בנו של רבי
אחאי בגולה, U'chshemeis bno shel Reb Achai ba'gola, יושב עליו שבעה ושלשים.
yashav alav shiva u'shloshim. And here's a case of a son, right?
It was שבעה ושלשים. shiva u'shloshim, So anyway, but what you see
is that the opinion of this case of the father, שבעה ושלשים,
shiva u'shloshim, that was a דעת יחיד. daas yachid. Now if you
wanted to have any דעת יחיד daas yachid that you knew you
could safely completely reject, it would be אלישע בן אבויה. Elisha ben
Avuya. So even though it was with זקנים, zkeinim, it wasn't only
whatever, that's a דעת יחיד, daas yachid, we don't rule like that.
But again, it's fascinating because there's nothing in this ברייתא braisa that
says special about the idea of אביו ואמו. aviv v'imo. That was
just the case, and right afterwards follows the case of a son,
right? So it sounds like the אשמעתא ashmata of this ברייתא braisa
is that for all relatives, שבעה shiva ושלשים, v'shloshim, there's no idea
of שמועה רחוקה. shmuah rehoka. Anyway, we are bracketing that opinion and
we are saying there's always שמועה רחוקה, shmuah rehoka, even for אביו
ואמו, aviv v'imo, and it would only be one day. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, איני, eini, is this really true?
והא רב בר אחוה דרבי חייא, V'ha Rav bar achvei d'Rebbi Chiya,
רב, Rav, who was the son of רבי חייא's Rebbi Chiya's sister,
דהוא בר אחתיה דרבי חייא, dehu bar achatei d'Rebbi Chiya, and also
the son of רבי חייא's Rebbi Chiya's brother, דהוא בר אחוה דרבי
חייא. dehu bar achvei d'Rebbi Chiya. So this רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya
had two half siblings, one on his father's side, one on his
mother's side, and they they weren't related to one another. You can
figure that one out. We're getting close to יבמות. Yevamos. So anyway,
but okay, anyway, so they were married to one another. So רבי
חייא's Rebbi Chiya's brother and his sister, who were half-siblings, were married
to one another, and the child was רב. Rav. So רב Rav
was רבי חייא's Rebbi Chiya's nephew on both sides. So כי סליק
להתם, Ki salik l'hasam, when he went up ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
אמר ליה amar lei to רבי חייא, Rebbi Chiya, אבא קיים? abba
kayam? Is father alive? So there's a whole question exactly how to
read this exchange, but the basic פשט pshat is that רבי חייא's
Rebbi Chiya's brother and sister had died, רב's Rav's father and mother,
and רב Rav was not simply want to sort of say it
outright. So רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya said to him, is father alive?
Presumably is your father alive? אמר ליה, Amar lei, אימא קיימת, imma
kayemes, my mother's alive. Or some say he said, ask me about
my mother. אמר ליה, Amar lei, okay, אימא קיימת? imma kayemes? Is
your mother alive? אמר ליה, Amar lei, אבא קיים. abba kayam. Well,
ask me about my father. Or my father is alive. Again, it's
very funny, like is to be said rhetorically. There's a whole discussion
in רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos exactly how to read the exchange,
but the point was he was he was like he was, you
know, avoiding answering the question, and and it was clear that the
answer was no, they're not, but he didn't want to say it
directly. So he found out,
so רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya found out that his brother and sister
died. So אמר ליה לשמעיה, amar lei l'shamayei, he said to his
attendant, חלוץ לי מנעלי, chalotz li minali, take off my shoe, והולך,
v'holeich, because an אבל avel can't wear shoes, והולך אחרי כלי לבית
המרחץ, v'holeich acharai keilai l'veit hamerchatz, but take, you know, my my
clothes to the bathhouse because I'll be going to the bathhouse later
today. Now it wasn't like he had such an urgent need to
go to the bathhouse, but he did it in order to demonstrate
the הלכה. halacha. שמע מינה תלת, Shma mina tlas, we can infer
from this three things. שמע מינה אבל אסור בנעילת הסנדל, Shma mina
avel assur b'neilat hasandal, an
אבל avel doesn't wear shoes, cause that's what he did to
demonstrate the practice.
ושמע
מינה שמועה רחוקה אינה
נוהגת אלא יום אחד,
U'shma mina shmuah
rehoka eina
noheges ela yom echad, that a שמועה רחוקה shmuah rehoka is only
one day and which is, you know, the earlier discussion. ושמע מינה,
U'shma mina, and you can also infer from this that מקצת היום
ככולו, miktzas hayom k'kulo, that even part of the day, even if
it was only one day, you only have to do part of
that one day because the later on in the day he was
going to go to the bathhouse. Okay. So anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says, so why is this an issue? Because this is an
issue because before we had a story with רבי אחאי, Rebbi Achai,
where was it? This is רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya and before the
story was, hold on a minute, previous right before it. Right.
Oh, שמת בנו של רבי אחאי, shemeis bno shel Reb Achai, right.
So before we had רבי אחאי Rebbi Achai who did a full
who did full and here was רבי חייא, Rebbi Chiya, so the
גמרא Gemara says, רבי חייא לחודיה ורבי אחאי לחודיה, Rebbi Chiya l'chudei
v'Rebbi Achai l'chudei, it's not the same person. Okay. אמר רבי יוסי
בר אבין, Amar Rebbi Yosi bar Abin, שמע שמועה קרובה ברגל, shama
shmuah krova baregel, ולמוצאי רגל נעשית רחוקה. u'l'motzei regel naasis rehoka.
So what happens if day thirty falls out during the רגל? regel?
So you heard before it was days before it had been thirty
days. You actually heard within the first thirty days, but the person
didn't have a chance to observe it until after the רגל. regel.
So is that called a שמועה קרובה shmuah krova or a שמועה
רחוקה? shmuah rehoka? So עולה לו ואינו נוהג אלא יום אחד. oleh
lo v'eino noheig ela yom echad. So that counts, now it doesn't
count in the same way before, before it counted to deduct the
total number of days. Here it counts in the sense that it's
like the person heard only after the רגל regel and therefore it's
counted as a שמועה רחוקה shmuah rehoka and the person only observes
one day. ותני רבי אדא מן קיסרי קמיה דרבי יוחנן, V'sani Rebbi
Adda min Kisari kamei d'Rebbi Yochanan, now that's by רגל. regel. רגל
Regel as we know is more fundamentally contrary and you know contradicts
אבילות. aveilus. But now we're gonna say it even by שבת. Shabbos.
שמע שמועה קרובה בשבת, Shama shmuah krova beShabbos, somebody heard on day
thirty on שבת, Shabbos, when it was first within the thirty days
and you can't observe it on שבת, Shabbos, ולמוצאי שבת נעשית רחוקה,
u'l'motzei Shabbos naasis rehoka, and after שבת Shabbos then it was already
day thirty-one. So אינה נוהג אלא יום אחד, einah noheg ela yom
echad, so it's only one day again. So that's quite fascinating, even
though you hear it and
your response to it is within the first thirty days, again, it's
the question is when is the practice being done that determines whether
it can still have the meaning of שבעה ושלושים. shiva u'shloshim. And
I think what you see from this again is because there's a
question I phrased before, why should there be a difference of קרובה
ורחוקה? krova u'rechoka? The person's first off, the person had heard about
it, but the question is the objective reality of to what degree
is are these practices sort of connected to the death? But it's
not just the person's own subjective expression. So if the practices are
more distant, then what's this guy just to sitting שבעה? shiva? The
guy died a year ago. Right? It's just not, you know, in
a sort of objective way can as much connected to the death.
So then the focus is more when the practices are observed, not
when the person finds out. So although sort of at the emotional,
psychological level the person found out within the first thirty days, as
the practice won't be observed until afterwards, that defines it as a
שמועה רחוקה, shmua rechoka, and therefore it's only going to be one
day and not the full שבעה. shiva. Okay, and now the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
קורע או אינו קורע. Koreah o eino koreah. Do you do קריעה
kria or not, does a person do קריעה kria in a case
of this scenario? And now it's not exactly clear what the גמרא
Gemara is asking. You could say it's a general question, does a
person do קריעה kria by a שמועה רחוקה? shmua rechoka? But תוספות
Tosafos says no, it's assumed that you don't do קריעה kria by
שמועה רחוקה. shmua rechoka. The question is in this case where the
person heard during the רגל regel or שבת Shabbos and after the
רגל regel or שבת Shabbos it was after thirty days. So again,
קריעה kria of all the practices is the one that sort of
the act of קריעה, kria, not just wearing torn clothes, but the
act of קריעה kria is the expression of grief, of the person's
subjective expression of grief. And we have acts of קריעה kria being
done for things that are not related to death, רואה ספר תורה
שנשרף, roeh sefer torah shenisraf, other types of things. So the question
is in this case where within the first thirty days the person
heard, but they didn't have an opportunity to observe until after thirty
days because it was שבת Shabbos or רגל, regel, would they still
do קריעה kria or not? Okay, assuming if it was all after
thirty days they would not. So קורע או אינו קורע, Koreah o
eino koreah, that's the question.
אמר רבי מני Amar Rabbi Mani אינו קורע, eino koreah, the person
does not do קריעה. kria. אמר רבי חנינא Amar Rabbi Chanina קורע,
koreah, the person does
קריעה. kria. אמר ליה רבי מני לרבי חנינא, Amar lei Rabbi Mani
l'Rabbi Chanina, בשלמא לדידי דאמינא אינו קורע, bishlama l'didi d'amina eino koreah,
it works for me, I say a person doesn't do קריעה, kria,
היינו
דלא איכא אבילות שבעה, hainu d'lo ika aveilus shiva, and because if
a person isn't observing שבעה, shiva, there's no sense you don't do
קריעה kria without שבעה shiva for all seven days. אלא לדידך דאמרת
קורע, Ella l'didach d'amart koreah, but you, you say do קריעה, kria,
קריעה בלא שבעה מי איכא, kria belo shiva mi ika, do you
ever have an act of קריעה kria done not in the context
of an observance of שבעה? shiva? So the גמרא Gemara says, ולא?
V'lo? Do you not? והתניא, V'hatanya, איסי אבוה דרבי זירא, Issi avuh
d'Rabbi Zeira, ואמרי לה אחוה דרבי זירא, v'amri lah achuh d'Rabbi Zeira,
קמיה דרבי זירא, kamia d'Rabbi Zeira, so either Rabbi Zeira's father or
brother taught in front of him: מי שאין לו חלוק לקרוע, Mi
she'ein lo chaluk likroa, a person doesn't have a shirt, you know,
he tells all of his clothes are borrowed, a person's not allowed
to do קריעה kria on borrowed clothes, ונזדמן לו בתוך שבעה, venizdamen
lo betoch shiva, and then he gets his own shirt during שבעה,
shiva, קורע, koreah,
he would do קריעה. kria. לאחר שבעה, Le'achar shiva, after שבעה, shiva,
אינו קורע, eino koreah, he would not do קריעה. kria. Okay, so
that seems to be consistent, קריעה kria only occurs in the context
of שבעה. shiva. But then עני רבי זירא בתריה, Ani Rabbi Zeira
basreh, but then Rabbi Zeira responded: במה דברים אמורים, Bameh devarim amurim,
when is that true? בחמשה מתי מצוה, B'chamisha misei mitzvah, by again,
the five relatives who are not mother and father. אבל על אביו
ועל אמו, Aval al aviv v'al imo,
but for a person's mother and father, קורע והולך, koreah v'holech, you
do קריעה, kria, a person would do קריעה kria even after the
שבעה. shiva. So you see here too, person should you can do
קריעה kria without the context of שבעה. shiva. So the גמרא Gemara
says: כי תניא ההיא לכבוד אביו ואמו. Ki tanya hahee lichvod aviv
v'imo. Fine, but that's because specifically for the honor of mother and
father. But the general rule still would be you do not do
קריעה kria without a שבעה. shiva. Now of course by saying mother
and father is different, it raises the questions of okay, but what
if it was a case of mother and father? What if there
was a case of a שמועה רחוקה shmua rechoka of mother and
father, would you do קריעה? kria? What if there was a case
of a שמועה קרובה shmua krova during רגל regel that after the
רגל regel became רחוקה, rechoka, would the person do קריעה kria if
it was a mother and father as opposed to somebody else? That's
not clear. Right, this is a scenario where a person is observing
a normal שבעה shiva and didn't have a בגד beged to do
קריעה kria on. But what would be the case if the person
actually had a שמועה רחוקה, shmua rechoka, would there be קריעה kria
for mother and father, would that be an aspect of כיבוד אב
ואם? kibbud av v'em? Not clear from the גמרא, Gemara, that's a
whole discussion in תוספות. Tosafos.
Okay, we will end here.
Have to keep on working not to get more behind.